A Guide to the St. John's Academy Records, 1833-1899
Alexandria Library, Local History/Special Collections
Alexandria Library, Local History/Special Collections
St. John's Academy Records 1833-1899
Alexandria Library, Local History/Special Collections
4
2 boxes (1.25 linear feet)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Annual Circular and bound The Academy Journal volumes purchased in 1980. Rest of collection purchased prior to 1980, source unknown. Grand Roll of St. John's Academy purchased in April 1997.
Biographical/Historical Information
St. John's Academy was established in 1833, and moved to a location at 57 South Royal Street (on the corner of Duke Street) in 1834. Rev. John Smith was the first principal; he was succeeded in turn by Rev. Stephen L. Dubuisson in 1837, Mr. John H. Kellenberger in 1839, and Mr. Hugh C. McLaughlin shortly thereafter. The school closed in 1841 when McLaughlin left Alexandria, but reopened in 1847 under R.L. Carne, Jr. A primary school, in addition to the older boys' school, was added in the 1850s. The upper school, additionally, was a military academy.
Scope and Content
The collection consists primarily of student records and student newspapers. There are several miscellaneous items as well. Topics covered include: school organization, rules of behavior, student achievement, student names, places of residence and dates of attendance, and academic subjects and undertakings.
Arrangement
The collection is divided into the following five series, arranged as indicated within parentheses:
Series I: Student Activities (alphabetical)
Series II: Clippings, 1840-1899 (chronological by year)
Series III: Miscellaneous (alphabetical)
Series IV: The Academy Journal, 1866-1885 (chronological by year)
Series V: Student Records, 1833-1896 (chronological)
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Other Finding Aid
Index to St. John's Academy Journal in separate card catalog. See "A" drawer for key to citation. Guide which includes folder list.
Related Material
History of St. John's Academy, 1833-1895 by Allan W. Robbins in Alexandria History 5 (1983).
Vertical file - Alexandria - St. John's Academy
Index Terms
Schools--Virginia--Alexandria
Contents List
- Student Activities (Box-folder 4A:1-3)
  - A Public Entertainment..., [1850s?] (Box-folder 4A:1)
  - Homework, n.d. (Box-folder 4A:2)
  - Intended Retirement of R.L. Carne..., 1892 (Box-folder 4A:3)
- Clippings (Box-folder 4A:4)
  - Clippings, 1840-1899 (Box-folder 4A:4)
- Miscellaneous (Box-folder 4A:5-7)
  - Andrews Latin Lessons (Academy bookplate), 1864 (Box-folder 4A:5)
  - Correspondence from William H. Sweeney (teacher) to John T. Riordan, 1886 (Box-folder 4A:6)
  - 50th Anniversary Speech, 1883 (Box-folder 4A:7)
- The Academy Journal (Box-folder 4A:8-15; 4B:7-8)
  - The Academy Journal (bound), December 25, 1866-June 10, 1868 (Box-folder 4A:8)
  - The Academy Journal, 1878 (Box-folder 4A:9)
  - The Academy Journal, 1879 (Box-folder 4A:10)
  - The Academy Journal, 1880 (Box-folder 4A:11)
  - The Academy Journal, 1881 (Box-folder 4A:12)
  - The Academy Journal, 1882 (Box-folder 4A:13)
  - The Academy Journal, 1883 (Box-folder 4A:14)
  - The Academy Journal, 1885 (Box-folder 4A:15)
  - The Academy Journal (bound), April 1872-August 1882 (Box-folder 4B:7)
  - The Academy Journal (bound), October 1882-August 1992 (Box-folder 4B:8)
- Student Records (Box-folder 4A:16; 4B:1-6, 9)
  - Annual Circular 13th-21st Sessions, 1851-1860 (Box-folder 4A:16)
  - Graduation certificate of Charles Deidel, 1876 (Box-folder 4B:1)
  - Accounts Ledger, 1860-1867 (Box-folder 4B:2)
  - Grand Roll, 1st-63rd Sessions, 1833-1896 (Box-folder 4B:3)
  - Register, 27th Session, 1865-1866 (Box-folder 4B:4)
  - Register, 29th Session, 1867-1868 (Box-folder 4B:5)
  - Register, 30th Session, 1868-1869 (Box-folder 4B:6)
  - Grand Roll of St. John's Academy, 1833-1838, Reconstructed 1847-April 1865 (Box-folder 4B:9)